SAI KUMAR

+1 940-333-4226 | saikumar8java@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Highly accomplished and experienced Core Java Developer with comprehensive mastery of all Java packages. Expert at both local and global vendor networks. Able to work independently with little to no supervision as well as functioning as an excellent team player. AWS Certified Developer | Certified SAFe® 5 Practitioner (Scaled Agile)

EDUCATION

Chicago State University | Master of Science (MS) in Computer Science | GPA: 3.9Aug 2021Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University | Bachelor of Technology | GPA: 3.8May 2018

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Java, Spring Boot, Angular JS, React, Verilog, Bootstrap, Node.js, Auto IT, OOP

Database Management: MYSQL, PostgreSQL, AWS, SQL Server DB,

Operating Systems: Windows 7 and 10, Linux, Real Time Operating System.

Web Application Frameworks: JavaScript, HTML5, CSS, PHP

Work Management Tool: Agile, Waterfall, JIRA, Scrum-Kanban, TDD

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

SHURE Incorporated

Software Engineer 2

Sep 2021 – Present

- Designed and developed software for Spring Framework based SOAP and REST based Web services that met the requirements of a **Retail customer application** in an Agile environment with **Java, RestAPI, Microservices.**
- Used HTML, CSS, Angular, Java, Spring Boot, MySQL for the development, and Jasmine and Karma for Unit testing. Enhanced the readability and performance of existing program using lambdas and hashing techniques.
- Improved the performance of existing SQL queries by 50% using indexes and common table expressions.
- Working with **collaborative Scrum-based Agile Methodologies**, which provides an accurate time estimate, more efficient for design implementation, test driven development, writing documentation, production, work on code reviews, retrospective.
- Experience in understanding and modifying whole **Software Development Life Cycle** (SDLC requirements, design, development, unit testing, deployment, Updating/Modifying, requirement analysis, functional/design specifications, Test plans designing.

Software Engineer May 2021 – August 2021

- Implemented Java EE components using Spring MVC, Spring IOC, Spring transactions and Spring security modules. Working proficiency in Core Java development toolset to design, develop, test, deploy, maintain and improve software.
- Automating the process of creating and assigning tickets on JIRA using REST service in Jenkins to ensure code quality.
- Application deployment using Git, Jenkins, CI/CD, Bitbucket. **APIs, microservices, and libraries that enable scalability**, reliability and make it super simple **for customers to consume** our offerings.

NCR Corporation Hyderabad, India
Software Engineer Dec 2018 – Jan 2020

- Worked in Financial Banking and Retail Sector, focusing on secure transactions of ATM.
- Improved the Customer experience by developing a web dashboard that displays the encryption status and detailed info using Angular by fetching the data from the API.
- Built and productionalized efficient Spring Boot Java Microservices, Kafka with REST APIs for Easy Pay installments feature in Fairstone system following Test Driven Design using JUnit.
- Migration of BIOS Access Utilities from Auto IT into C# to increase security to ATM software, enabling Internal Customers to manage access to BIOS, change passwords, and boot ATM remotely, which **improves the performance by 35%.**
- Introduced and developed Task Manger application to deploy Intel Firmware automatically, which saves 25% of the workforce.

Associate Software Engineer

Jul 2018 - Nov 2018

- Designing and developing different application tiers using Java, SpringBoot, multi-threading, patterns.
- Research, predictive analytics and executing Regression Test Cases, manage change requests, bug fixes, and troubleshoot issues.
- Troubleshooting ATM server issues that contains crucial ATM Decryption keys which can impact the customers data, system
 performance and reporting of vulnerability analysis. Strong focus on JIRA involving custom projects, workflows, fields,
 dashboards and reports configurations.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Warehouse Management System

(Java, Springboot MVC, JavaScript, MySQL, HTML, CSS)

Facial Authentication Cash Withdraw

(Java, Python, Angular JS, Embedded Circuits)

Pizza Kitchen Application

(Java, MYSQL, JavaScript)

ICU Patient Monitoring System (IOT)

(C#, ASP.NET, SQL, HTML, CSS, IC, pic 18F452, WIFI module, Humidity Sensor)